<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Religious covenanting directed, and covenant-keeping perswaded: presented, in a sermon preached before the Right Honourable Thomas Adams Lord Major, and the right worshipfull the sheriffs, and aldermen his brethren, and the rest of the Common-Councel of the famous City of London, January 14. 1645. Upon which day the solemne League and Covenant was renewed by them and their officers, with prayer and fasting, at Michael Basing-shaw, London. / By Simeon Ash minister of the Gospel.</title>
            <author>Ashe, Simeon, d. 1662.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1646</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 60 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 14 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A75711</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A3965</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E327_5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R200647</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99861334</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99861334</idno>
            <idno type="VID">113467</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A75711)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 113467)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 53:E327[5])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Religious covenanting directed, and covenant-keeping perswaded: presented, in a sermon preached before the Right Honourable Thomas Adams Lord Major, and the right worshipfull the sheriffs, and aldermen his brethren, and the rest of the Common-Councel of the famous City of London, January 14. 1645. Upon which day the solemne League and Covenant was renewed by them and their officers, with prayer and fasting, at Michael Basing-shaw, London. / By Simeon Ash minister of the Gospel.</title>
                  <author>Ashe, Simeon, d. 1662.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 22, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by G.M. for Tho. Underhill at the signe of the Bible in Wood-street.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M.DC.XLVI. [1646]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Psalms LXXVI, 11 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Fast-day sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Covenant theology --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:113467:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>RELIGIOVS COVENANTING DIRECTED, AND Covenant-keeping perſwaded: <hi>PRESENTED,</hi> In a SERMON preached before the Right Honourable <hi>Thomas Adams</hi> Lord Major, and the Right Worſhipfull the Sheriffs, and Alder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men his brethren, and the reſt of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Councel of the famous City of LONDON, <hi>January,</hi> 14. 1645.</p>
            <p>Upon which day the ſolemne League and Covenant was renewed by them and their Officers, with Prayer and Faſting, at <hi>Michael Baſing-ſhaw, London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>Simeon Aſh</hi> Miniſter of the Goſpel.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>When thou ſhalt vow a vow unto the Lord thy God, thou ſhalt not ſlack to pay it, for the Lord thy God will require it of thee, and it would be ſin in thee.</hi>
               <bibl> Deut. 23. 21.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <hi>I will bring the ſword upon you, that ſhall avenge the quarrell of my Covenant.</hi>
               <bibl> Lev. 26. 25.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>G. M.</hi> for <hi>Tho. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderhill</hi> at the ſigne of the Bible in Wood-ſtreet. M. DC. XLVI.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:113467:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:113467:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE <hi>THOMAS ADAMS</hi> Lord Major, AND THE RIGHT WORSHIPFULL The Sheriffs and Aldermen his Brethren, and to the reſt of the Honourable Court of Common Councel of the City of LONDON.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His plain Sermon which attended your ſervice of</hi> Covenant-renewing <hi>from the Pulpit, comes now from the Preſſe, in obedience to your command, to do you and the publike ſome further ſervice. If upon the peruſall of that which you heard preached, it may pleaſe the Lord to quicken your zeal in Covenant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keeping, I ſhall have occaſion to bleſſe his Name with a joyfull heart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The zeal of the Common-Councell of</hi> London, <hi>in renewing their ſolemne League and Covenant, rings thorow the ſeverall Counties of the Kingdom of</hi> England: <hi>and I am confident, that the ſound thereof hath been heard in many other Kingdoms: And doubtleſſe there are often enquiries, and earneſt expectations to hear what</hi> Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don <hi>now doth in the purſuance of their Covenant heretofore taken, and now again ſolemnly renewed with holy faſting and prayer.</hi> A City ſet upon an hill cannot be hid; <hi>your practices have had, and will have ſtrong influences into the ſeverall parts of this Land, and into other Nations: You have formerly and lately done well and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily in reſpect to your Covenant: I pray God, that your continued holy zeal may affect and fire many in other Countries in faithfull Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant-keeping.
<pb facs="tcp:113467:3"/> God forbid, that you ſhould ever deſerve thus to be ſtigmatized, either by God or men;</hi> Their heart was not right with God, neither were they ſtedfaſt in their Covenant, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 78. 37.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I ſhall not need to tell you, that our ſolemne League and Covenant is despiſed, devided, aſperſed and oppoſed by too many: for that which you may read in Pamphlets, and hear from ſome Pulpits and other places, doth make you both eye-witneſſes and ear-witneſſes of this evil, which ſhould be greatly bewailed. This contradiction, this oppoſition ſhould increaſe your gracious heat for your God. Fire gives out the moſt ſcorching heat in the coldeſt weather.</hi> It is time for thee, Lord, to worke (<hi>ſaith David</hi>) for they have made void thy Law. Therefore I love thy Commandements above gold, yea above fine gold. Therefore I eſteem all thy precepts concerning all things to be right, and I hate every falſe way, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. 126, 127, 128.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>My ſoul deſires, that according to the guidance of that wiſedom which is from above, you all may make the like gracious improvement of the checks and affronts which you meet with, in your Covenant-keeping. By how much the more, any others do plot and practiſe to hinder the glorious worke of Church-reformation, by ſo much the more do you conſult and act, to expedite and perfect it. By how much the more any others ſtrive and ſtudy to maintain Popery, Prelacie, Schiſme, Hereſie. by ſo much the more, do you ſet your ſelves againſt ſuch matters, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing destructive to the welfare both of Church and ſtate. By how much the more others deſigne and endeavour to break the brotherly union between</hi> England <hi>and</hi> Scotland, <hi>by ſo much the more do you lay forth your ſelves to maintain it. And that your zeal in theſe kindes may appear to your ſelves and others to be pure and ſincere, let it be your chief and conſtant care, to reforme your ſelves and all yours, in every thing, according to the will of God: That you all may in theſe parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars and in all things elſe, approve yaur ſelves faithfull both to God and man, in holy Covenant-keeping, ſhall be the prayer of him, who is</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your ſervant, in, and for Jeſus Chriſt, SIM: ASH.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Feb. 24<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:113467:3"/>
            <head>RELIGIOVS COVENANTING DIRECTED.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>PSAL. 76. II.</bibl> Vow and pay unto the Lord your God.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Text perſwades a double duty. 1. To make vows. 2. To pay vows unto the Lord our God. From whence two truths, ſeaſonable for the ſervice of the day, fall naturally, and eaſily, without forcing, into our conſideration.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>1</label> 
               <hi>That Gods people must make religious vows, as his hand of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence doth lead them forth thereunto.</hi> 
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>2</label> 
               <hi>That ſuch vows being made, must be payed unto the Lord our God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the handling of the former of theſe propoſitions, I ſhall briefly give you, 1. The explication; 2. The application thereof.</p>
            <p>The explication of the point I ſhall diſpatch under theſe three heads. 1. The Act required, <hi>vow.</hi> 2. The Agents, or perſons upon whom this duty is preſſed: This the following words ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe. <hi>All thoſe that be round about him.</hi> 3. The providences, whereby God calleth forth to this practice <hi>of making vows.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, Holy vows are the ſolemn engagements of the ſoul unto the Lord, according to his will: <hi>If a man vow a vow unto the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:113467:4"/> Lord, or ſwear an oath, to binde his ſoul with a bond,</hi> Numb. 30. 2. To vow, to ſwear, and to covenant, are in Scripture phraſe equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valent, importing the ſame thing, <hi>Jonathan made a Covenant with David, And Jonathan cauſed David to ſwear again,</hi> 1 Sam. 29. 16, 17. Here I may not ſpend time, in diſcourſing concerning the ſeverall ſorts of vows, which might be ſpoken to, under theſe, or ſuch like heads. 1. They are either made to God, or man. 2. Of things neceſſary, or arbitrary. 3. Explicite, or implicite, mentall, or vocall. 4. Aſſertory, or promiſſory. But let it be ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient, that I now ſuggeſt thus much: That the Text is to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood of ſuch vows, as are promiſſory obligations unto the Lord. And from hence I ſhall perſwade and direct the managing of ſuch vows unto God, as are neceſſary and openly unfolded to every ordinary underſtanding, in the ſolemn League and Covenant this day to be renewed.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the Actors in this duty are deſcribed to be ſuch, as are <hi>round about the Lord.</hi> The Pſalmiſt hath reference to <hi>Numb.</hi> 2. 2. where <hi>Iſrael</hi> was commanded <hi>to pitch</hi> their Tents round <hi>about the Tabernacle,</hi> which was a ſigne of Gods ſpeciall preſence. And this phraſe (as I conceive) deſcribeth Gods people by a double character. 1. Their ſpeciall attendance upon God, their readineſſe to receive and obey his commands: As the four and twenty El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, are ſaid, <hi>Rev.</hi> 4. 4. to be <hi>round about the Throne,</hi> as pres'd to praiſe the Lord. 2. Gods ſpeciall preſence in the midſt of them, to hear prayers, and to performe promiſes, for their preſervation and welfare in every kinde; <hi>who hath God ſo nigh unto them, as the Lord our God, in all things, that we call upon him for?</hi> Deu. 4. 7.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, the call unto this imployment I ſhall note under a five fold providence from the Lord.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Sinfull defections from God, that by means of religious vow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, his backſliding people might be recovered: <hi>Our fathers have trespaſſed and done that which is evil in the eyes of the Lord our God, and have forſaken him, and have turned away their face from the habitation of the Lord, and turned their backs. Alſo they have ſhut up the doors of the porch, and put out the lamps, and have not burnt incenſe, nor offered burnt offerings, in the holy place unto the God of Iſrael. Now it is in my heart</hi> (ſaith <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zekiah</hi>)
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:113467:4"/> 
               <hi>to make a Covenant with the Lord God of Iſrael,</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 29. 6, 7, 10. Thus likewiſe the people of God reſolved in the dayes of <hi>Ezra: We have treſpaſſed againſt our God,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Now therefore, let us make a Covenant with our God,</hi> Ezra 10. 2, 3.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Sad diſcoveries of divine diſpleaſure, that by holy covenant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing preſent judgements might be removed, and future evils pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented: <hi>The wrath of the Lord was upon Judah and Jeruſalem; and he hath delivered them to trouble, to aſtoniſhment and to hiſſing, as ye ſee with your eyes. For lo our fathers have fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len by the ſword, and our ſons, and our daughters, and our wives are in captivity for this. Now it is in mine heart</hi> (ſaith <hi>Hezekiah) to make a covenant with the Lord God of Iſrael, that his fierce wrath may turne away from us,</hi> 2 Chron. 29. 8, 9, 10.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Famous experiences of Gods goodneſſe, that by the right uſe of religions vows his Majeſty may be praiſed, and his providen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces improved. The exhortation in the Text was grounded upon ſome ſuch occaſion, as many verſes in the Pſalme declare: <hi>The ſtout-hearted are spoiled, they have ſlept their ſleep, and none of the men of might have found their hands,</hi> ver. 5. <hi>At thy rebuke, O God of Jacob, both the chariot and horſe are caſt into a dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſleep,</hi> ver. 6. <hi>When God aroſe in judgement to ſave all the meek of the earth,</hi> ver. 8. Hence follows, <hi>vow and pay,</hi> &amp;c. Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters judge, that this Pſalm was penned, upon <hi>Aſhurs</hi> overthrow, whereupon <hi>many brought gifts unto the Lord unto Jeruſalam,</hi> 2 Chron. 32. 23. according to the advice given in the words im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly following the Text, <hi>Bring preſents unto him that ought to be feared.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. Defective improvements (if any improvements at all) of Gods favourable adminiſtrations, that by foederall engagements his people might be bettered: <hi>Theſe are the words of the cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant which the Lord commanded Moſes</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Ye have ſeen all that the Lord did before your eyes, even in the land of Egypt,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>The great temptations, and thoſe great miracles: yet the Lord hath not given you an heart to perceive, and eyes to ſee, and ears to hear unto this day,</hi> Deut. 29. 1, 2, 3, 4. This is propounded as one ground of the Covenant renewed, whereof we reade in the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing verſes.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:113467:5"/>5. Apparent danger of ſeduction and departure from God. In this regard Gods ſervants have afreſh obliged themſelves to his Majeſty, for their own eſtabliſhment and preſervation: <hi>Ye stand this day before the Lord, to enter into covenant with the Lord thy God, leſt there ſhould be amongſt you any, whoſe heart turneth away from the Lord,</hi> Deut. 29. 10, 12, 18.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">V;ſe </seg>1</label> The application of this point followeth; which ſerves in the firſt place to informe you of your call to <hi>covenant-renewing,</hi> the intended ſervice of this day. For give me leave to appeal unto your conſciences, <hi>Right Honourable, right Worſhipfull, and much respected Citizens,</hi> whether all the five fore-mentioned parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars, do not fully reach you and take hold upon you, both in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of Gods dealings with you, and your miſcarriages towards him, ſince you at firſt took the ſolemne League and Covenant. And here I ſhall make bold to propound unto you ſome ſhort in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrogatories, under the five fore-mentioned heads, to which I wiſh your hearts may returne anſwers, as in the preſence of the All<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowing God.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Are you not guilty of ſinfull declinings in a great degree from your former engagements unto the Lord? Have you not loſt your firſt love? Have not the matters of Gods houſe been much ſleighted and neglected? Hath not your care to preſerve the truth of Religion from corruption been much abated? Have you not connived at the ſpreading of pernicious errours in this City? Hath not your zeal againſt ſchiſme and ſinfull ſeparations from our Church Aſſemblies been very much cooled? Is not your love to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards our Brethren of <hi>Scotland</hi> in a great meaſure leſſened? Have not your vigorous endeavours to promote the ſetling of Chriſts government in our Congregations been wofully diminiſhed? And have you not been lamentably wanting in labouring the thorow reformation of your ſelves and families? Which of you, hath ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to exceed, to excell others, in advancing the power of godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in your converſation? Doubtleſſe theſe and ſuch like back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlidings from former engagements, may well warrant your Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant-renewing with your God.</p>
            <p>Secondly, None of you can be ignorant of the manifold, mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt diſcoveries of Gods heavy diſpleaſure againſt this poor trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling Kingdom. Hath not the Lord <hi>delivered us up unto trouble
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:113467:5"/> and aſtoniſhment,</hi> by his ſevere adminiſtrations? How many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands have fallen by the ſword of cruell war? What wofull de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolations are made in many Towns, yea Counties in this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, by the prevailing pitileſſe enemies? And ſhould not we read Gods wrath againſt our ſelves, in the abundance of blood which hath been ſhed, and the unhappy ſpoils which have been made in <hi>Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland?</hi> Beſides all this, I pray you conſider whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther theſe things do not proclaim and ſpeak alowd Gods anger? Our long looked for reformation in matters of Religion, is ſtill de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred: our hopes of the much-needed and much-deſired Diſcipline of Jeſus Chriſt, are ſtill diſappointed: the miſerable rents and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions in families, Congregations, Cities and Counties, by reaſon of different, yea contrary opinions and practices, in wayes of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, are wonderfully increaſed. And have we not in theſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gards reaſon to renew our Covenant, that the wrath of the Lord may be turned from us?</p>
            <p>Thirdly, God hath often <hi>remembred us in our low eſtate, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe his mercy endureth for ever.</hi> Who can recount Gods many marvellous works for our ſafety and comfort? Have not our deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verances been wonderfull, and many of our victories little leſſe then miraculous? How often hath the ſubtiil enemy been infatua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, the ſtrong enemy weakned, and great Armies broken by a little ſtrength? I ſhall not need here to minde you of the many wonders which Gods Almighty hand hath wrought for us, both in the Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therne and Weſterne parts. And as for this City, how admirably and unexpectedly hath it been preſerved and provided for, in every kinde by the Lord? How many oppreſſions are we freed from, by Parliamentary authority, through the goodneſſe of our God? Therefore beſides other preſents of praiſe which God deſerves at our hands, we have juſt occaſion to preſent our ſelves unto his Higneſſe by Covenant-renewing.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Notwithſtanding our various and glorious expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riences of Gods patience and goodneſſe; Have we not too much cauſe thus to complain, that to this day we want hearts to huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band Gods remarkable providences, to his honour and our own ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage? Who loves God more, or who ſerves him better, becauſe of the great things he hath done for us? Is our faith in Gods pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes ſtronger? Is our fear of Gods diſpleaſure greater? Are we
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:113467:6"/> more zealous for the Lord of Hoſts, or more couragious for his truth, againſt errour? Dare we ſay that we do our utmoſt for the ſpeeding of Church-reformation, that we may not be over-run and undone by Sects, Schiſmes and confuſions? Therefore certainly, we have a call to renew our Covenant, to quicken our improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Gods gracious providences, both to his praiſe, others pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit, and our own further comfort in Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Fiftly and laſtly, That we may not fall from our ſtedfaſtneſſe, we have need to binde our ſelves yet further unto our God by ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne Covenant. Men are wont (as I have heard) to hoop their <hi>veſſels</hi> with iron bonds, in which they carry their ſtronger liquors beyond ſeas, that by the toſſings in the ſhip and the liquors working, the veſſels may not be broken into pieces, and the liquor loſt. And have not we more need to add the bond of a ſolemne Covenant to the bond of Gods ſacred commands, that we may not be broken from one another, nor divided from God in his truths and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly worſhips, in theſe broken, erroneons, ſtormy, tempeſtuous times?</p>
            <p>For 1. <hi>Emulation, variance, ſtrife, ſeditions, hereſies,</hi> are rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koned <note place="margin">Gal. 5.</note> up, by the Apoſtle, amongſt the works of the fleſh, unto which our corrupt natures do ſtrongly diſpoſe us.</p>
            <p>2. There are more then a good many of ſubtle, buſie factours in this City, to promote errours, ſchiſmes and factions of ſeverall ſorts, to draw diſciples after them, and to ſpread their infection amongſt people of all rankes and qualities.</p>
            <p>3. It is apparent, by too many inſtances, that divers perſons both wiſe and godly, have been deceived and drawn aſide from the wayes of truth, into the by-paths of errour and ſchiſme, and into practices of bitterneſſe (I will not ſay of how many kindes) againſt their brethren. Therefore in this reſpect, as in thoſe before mentioned, you have juſt cauſe to ſay one to another; <hi>Come, let us joyn our ſelves unto the Lord in a Covenant, never to be forgotten.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> Having thus far endeavoured to clear up your call unto Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant-renewing, I now proceed by way of exhortation, to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade your regular and reverentiall cautiouſneſſe in this weighty buſineſſe. Conſider the glorious Majeſty of God, unto whom vows are to be made; He <hi>ought to be feared,</hi> as our tranſlation
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:113467:6"/> renders the words following the Text: or, He <hi>is fear,</hi> as the Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall hath it. In which phraſe we have <hi>Nomen affectus, pro ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecto.</hi> God is a dreadfull and terrible Majeſty. And this doubtleſſe is added, to awe mens hearts, in the undertaking of ſuch like ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices. The advice of <hi>Solomon</hi> upon this ground is more open, <hi>Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ.</hi> 5. 2. <hi>Be not raſh with thy mouth, and let not thy heart be haſty to utter any thing before God, for God is in Heaven, and thou upon earth.</hi> In which counſell, the wiſe man hath ſpeciall reference unto vowing, as the following words declare.</p>
            <p>Now for your guidance in this great ſervice, I will give you briefly ſome plain and neceſſary rules.</p>
            <p n="1">1. You muſt Covenant <hi>knowingly.</hi> It is thus openly expreſſed, of them who covenanted in the dayes of <hi>Nehemiah, Every one having knowledge, and having underſtanding, they clave to their brethren, they entred into an oath to walke in Gods Law,</hi> Neh. 10. 29. Ignorance doth nothing well: the light of knowledge muſt guide our whole courſe. And in this buſineſſe of a ſacred vow, it is neceſſary that men know, both the nature of the duty, and the matter of the federall engagement. No man ſhould be moved by an implicite faith, but every one ſhould be fully perſwaded in his own minde. For as in other caſes, ſo in this, <hi>whatſoever is not of faith, is ſin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Repentance</hi> for former offences muſt precede, and prepare for Covenant-renewing. Thus it was with thoſe, who ſealed and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed the ſolemne Covenant in the time of <hi>Nehemiah,</hi> for they aſſembled themſelves to keep a religious Faſt (as we do this day) before they entered into the Covenant, <hi>Neh.</hi> 9. 1. In which exerciſe deep ſorrow for ſin was expreſſed, their particular evils were ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravated and largely confeſſed, themſelves were judged, and God was juſtified in his ſevere adminiſtrations: All theſe expreſſions of repentance, are manifeſt in that 9<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Chapter of <hi>Nehemiah,</hi> which then was the introduction to the Covenant. And doubtleſſe if we do not penitently bewail our former violations of Gods com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands and our own vows, we cannot with acceptation to God, or with comfort in our own hearts renew our Covenant with him this day.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Your <hi>hearts</hi> muſt go along with your vows. It is ſaid, <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Chron<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 15<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 15<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> That all Judah did ſwear with all their hearts<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:113467:7"/> And God will not take up with leſſe at our hands this day. It is no better then hypocriſie, to lift up hands before God, when <hi>the heart is far from him.</hi> We muſt in our judgements approve and reſolve upon the payment of our vows, and all our affections, both concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcible and iraſcible, muſt be upon the wing, according to the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious particularities expreſſed in the Covenant. The ſoul ſhould with love, joy and longings, worke towards the ſpeedy ſetling of Church-governement according to the word of God, and towards the maintaining of brotherly union between the two Kingdoms of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> together with the more full reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our ſelves and families. And O how ſhould your ſouls now riſe, in holy diſlike, in the hatred of, and in indignation againſt <hi>Popery, and all profaneneſſe,</hi> againſt <hi>Hereſies, Schiſme, deteſtable Neutrality,</hi> and whatſoever elſe it is, which is againſt God and the wellfare of theſe Kingdoms!</p>
            <p n="4">4. Our Covenanting muſt be accompanied with <hi>humility.</hi> 1. From the ſenſe of our own weakneſſes to keep touch with God, in comming up fully to the Covenant; we ſhould lean to his promiſe, and take hold on his ſtrength: Say, as the Church, <hi>Through God we ſhall do valiantly, Pſal.</hi> 60. 11. And as the bleſſed Apoſtle did; <hi>Phil.</hi> 4. 13. <hi>I can do all things through Jeſus Chriſt ſtrengthen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2. And being apprehenſive of our own unworthineſſe, to receive any ability from the Lord, ſeeing by our ſins, we have enfeebled our own ſpirits, therefore we ſhould humbly petition for divine aſſiſtance. Herein imitate <hi>David,</hi> who having thus in reſolution and promiſe expreſſed himſelf before God, <hi>I will keep thy statutes,</hi> he immediatly adds, <hi>O forſake me not utterly, Pſal.</hi> 119. 8. The more of the ſpirit of <hi>ſelf-deniall and prayer</hi> is in your hearts, when you take the Covenant, the more hope there will be of your keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it afterwards.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Come to the Covenant <hi>conſcientiouſly.</hi> Be not acted only by the appointments, expectations or practices of men in this par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular: Let not this be the alone motive upon your ſpirits; Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant-renewing is ordered by the <hi>Court of Common-Councel:</hi> But rather reaſon thus; The manifold providences of God before ſpecified, do call unto this ſervice, and therefore we will undertake it. If you reſpect not God in the worke, you ſhall loſe both accept <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 line">
                  <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <p n="6">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:113467:7"/>6. Covenant <hi>fiducially:</hi> If your ſpirits act ſincerely, according to the fore-named directions, then be you confident that the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence of this dayes ſervice will be comfortable. Although your weakneſſes are many and great, yet if your hearts be herein found upright with God, you may hopefully perſwade your ſelves that the Lord will ſo far regard his own ordinance, and have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect unto the mediation of Chriſt (<hi>the Meſſenger, the Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour of the new-Covenant</hi>) that your worke ſhall be crowned with good ſucceſſe. You heard before, that <hi>Enemy-conquering providences</hi> made way unto the exhortation in the Text, <hi>Vow and pay unto the Lord your God.</hi> And I conceive that the verſe following is conſiderable, being the language of faith; <hi>He ſhall cut off the ſpirit of Princes, he is terrible to the Kings of the earth:</hi> The moſt potent adverſaries of the Church ſhall be brought down, by holy Covenant-making and Covenant-keeping with God.</p>
            <p>Now this lets me into the conſideration of my next Doctrine;</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctr. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>That vows made, muſt be paid unto the Lord our God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Although a vow muſt not be made a bond of iniquity, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore unlawfull vows rather call for repentance then performance, (as <hi>Davids</hi> raſh revengefull reſolution againſt churliſh <hi>Nabal.</hi>)</p>
            <p>Yet ſuch Covenants as we make according to Gods will, we muſt make good, in conſcience to his commandment: <hi>Pay that which thou haſt vowed</hi> (ſaith <hi>Solomon,) Better it is that thou ſhouldeſt not vow, then that thou ſhouldest vow and not pay it. Suffer not thy mouth to cauſe thy fleſh to ſin,</hi> Eccleſ. 5. 4, 5. The Scribes and Phariſees were but ſleighty ſuperficiall Expoſitours of Gods Law, yet they were wont thus to <hi>publiſh Gods command: Thou ſhalt not forſwear thy ſelf, but ſhalt performe unto the Lord thine oaths,</hi> Mat. 5. 33.</p>
            <p>In the proſecution of this plain, profitable, ſeaſonable and neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary point, I ſhall faithfully endeavour three things. 1. <hi>To perſwade this duty by arguments.</hi> 2. <hi>To guide this practice by rules.</hi> 3. <hi>To promote your obedience herein, by ſome ſhort directions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The motives whereby we may be induced to make good our honeſt and holy vows, ſhall be caſt under ſeverall heads, that my <note place="margin">Motives.</note> progreſſe in them, may be the more eaſie and edifying.</p>
            <p n="1">1. From the nature of a vow in generall, and from ſundry
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:113467:8"/> circumſtances conſiderable in <hi>our Covenant</hi> particularly.</p>
            <p>In generall; 1. All vows are ſacred obligations upon our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences: <hi>If any</hi> (ſaith <hi>Moſes) vow a vow unto the Lord, or ſwear an oath, to binde his ſoul with a bond,</hi> Numb. 30. 2. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> In this reſpect the holy Pſalmiſt reſolved upon this duty, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 56. 12. <hi>Thy vows are upon me, O Lord, I will render praiſes:</hi> And doubtleſſe every gracious heart will be ſenſible of this great ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall engagement. 2. By means of vows we become Gods deb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors: Hence it is, that the Text calls for <hi>payment, Vow and pay.</hi> I here remember the ſpeech of the Prophet unto the poor widow, 2 <hi>King.</hi> 4. 7. <hi>Go ſell thine oyl, and pay the debt.</hi> And the Holy Ghoſt gives in this, as a note of a wicked man, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37. 21. <hi>He borroweth, and payeth not again.</hi> You <hi>Merchants,</hi> who have great dealings in the world, would you not be aſhamed to appear upon the <hi>Exchange,</hi> if you were not carefull to pay your debts unto men? Therefore, <hi>vow and pay unto the Lord your God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>More particularly, there are ſundry weighty circumſtances con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable, in regard of our <hi>ſolemn League and Covenant,</hi> which may worke our hearts unto ſerious reſolutions to keep it.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The materials of our Covenant are <hi>lawfull and juſtifiable;</hi> we vow to <hi>endeavour the extirpation of Popery, Prelacy, Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition, Hereſie, ſchiſme, profaneneſſe, and whatſoever ſhall be found to be contrary to ſound doctrine and the power of godlineſſe.</hi> And have we not good reaſon thus to do? For have not theſe things much endangered the welfare both of this Church and Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth already? and will not the indulging of ſuch matters, prove deſtructive both to our publike hopes and comforts? We vow ſincerely, really, conſtantly, through the grace of God, <hi>to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour the reformation of Religion, in Doctrine, worſhip, Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline and Government, according to the word of God, and the example of the beſt Reformed Churches.</hi> I ſhall not need to ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifie our engagements, <hi>to defend the Kings perſon and authority in the preſervation of the true Religion, to preſerve the priviledges of Parliament, as alſo to continue a firme peace and union be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Kingdoms of</hi> England <hi>and</hi> Scotland. Theſe and other things expreſſed in the Covenant, are by you Covenanters account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed juſt and equall. I remember <hi>Davids</hi> reſolution, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. 106. <hi>I have ſworn and I will perform it, that I will keep thy righteous
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:113467:8"/> judgements.</hi> And if we judge the materials of our Covenant righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, we ſhould in that regard lay the greater charge upon our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences to keep it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Our vows are <hi>deliberate.</hi> The nature of this ordinance hath been unfolded, the ſeverall Articles in the Covenant have been conſidered of, and therefore the rather to be obſerved. Raſh vows binde conſcience, if the keeping of them prove only in inexpedien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies prejudiciall to our ſelves, and contradict not any of Gods ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>binding laws. Therefore <hi>Solomon</hi> calling for the payment of vows, tells people, that they muſt not thinke to put off that obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, by ſaying, <hi>It was an errour, Eccl.</hi> 5. an inconſiderate overſight. And we all know, that when <hi>Iſrael</hi> was bound to the <hi>Gibeonites</hi> by an oath, through a miſtake, being over-reached by a cheat, <hi>All the Princes ſaid to all the Congregation, We have ſworn unto them by the Lord God of Iſrael, now therefore we may not touch them, Joſh.</hi> 9. 19. How then ſhall we be excuſed, if our premiditated vows be not performed?</p>
            <p n="3">3. We have vowed before many <hi>witneſſes.</hi> Men who ſtand much upon their credit and reputation in the world, will be taken with this argument. When King <hi>Herod</hi> was caught in a ſnare, by his heady vow, and being troubled, becauſe the dancing Damſell demanded the head of <hi>John</hi> the Baptiſt, it is ſaid, <hi>Nevertheleſſe for the oath ſake, and them which ſate with him at meat, he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded it to be given her, Mat.</hi> 14. 9. Conſider how many have ſeen you lift up your hands unto the moſt High poſſeſſour of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and earth, in holy Covenanting: Remember how many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands know that the vows of God are upon you, and be you hereby prevailed with to keep touch with him.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Hereto I might add the conſideration, both of the <hi>multitude of all rankes, qualities, callings in this Kingdom, in</hi> Scotland, <hi>Parliament-men, Souldiers, Citizens, Divines,</hi> &amp;c. who are here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in mutually engaged with us. I might alſo minde you of the often reiterations and renewings of your vows and Covenants: Doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe theſe things will not be ſleighted by them who are ingenuous; but I may not inſiſt upon them, having divers other heads of argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to ſpeak unto.</p>
            <p>The ſecond ſort of arguments to perſwade Covenant-keeping, ſhall be taken from our God, the only true and bleſſed God, unto
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:113467:9"/> whom our vows oblige us. And under this head theſe particulars are conſiderable: 1. His Majeſty takes exact notice of all ſuch engagements, together with all the circumſtances of time, place, companies, occaſions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which belong thereto: <hi>O God thou haſt heard my vows,</hi> ſaith <hi>David, Pſal</hi> 61. 5.</p>
            <p n="2">2. His Highneſſe well remembers theſe obligations: The Lord rounds <hi>Jacob</hi> in the ear with this <hi>Memento, I am the God of Bethel, where thou anointest the pillar, and where thou voweſt a vow unto me,</hi> Gen. 31. 13.</p>
            <p n="3">3. He calls for paiment, he will not be taken off from demand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his debt in this kinde: <hi>When thou ſhalt vow a vow unto the Lord thy God, thou ſhalt not be ſlack to pay it, for the Lord thy God will ſurely require it of thee,</hi> Deut. 23. 21.</p>
            <p n="4">4. He is the moſt High poſſeſſour and commander of Heaven and earth. The Pſalmiſt layes ſtrength upon this conſideration, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50. 14. <hi>Pay thy vows unto the moſt High.</hi> And this thought was prevailing upon the hearts of <hi>Jephihah</hi> and his daughter, in a caſe very difficult in a courſe very croſſe to the ſtream and ſtrength of naturall affection: you all know his vow, therefore I ſhall not need to name it, but marke I pray you the expreſſions, both of the father and of his childe, <hi>Judg.</hi> 11. 35, 36. <hi>I have opened my mouth</hi> (ſaith <hi>Jephthah) unto Jehovah, and I cannot go back. And ſhe ſaid to him, My father, if thou hast opened thy mouth unto Jehovah, do to me according to that which hath proceeded out of thy mouth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. He is a moſt faithfull Covenant-keeping God: <hi>He is God, the faithfull God, which keepeth Covenant and mercy,</hi> Deut. 7. 9. Although meer mercy move his Majeſty to make Covenant, yet will he make it good: How much more ſhould we keep our holy Covenants, which both duty and neceſſity call us to renew.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Although our well-doing, doth not, cannot reach the Lord with advantage, yet his Highneſſe will account himſelf honoured by our faithfullneſſe in Covenant: Hence it is, that theſe two du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties are conjoyned in the Scripture; <hi>Offer to God thankeſgiving, and pay thy vows unto the most High, Pſal.</hi> 50. 14. And <hi>Pſal.</hi> 65. 1. <hi>Praiſe waiteth for thee O God in Sion, and unto thee ſhall the vow be performed.</hi> Conſider I pray you, Do we not owe God praiſe? Do we not pray, <hi>Hallowed be thy Name?</hi> Will it not be
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:113467:9"/> our Honours to ſet the Crown on his head? Therefore let us all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve to performe <hi>our vows unto the Lord our God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The third head of arguments follows to be conſidered, and it is drawn from the various precious benefits to be received, by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientious <note place="margin">Motive 3.</note> Covenant-keeping with the Lord our God. 1. Care in this kinde will evidence our effectuall converſion to God. The Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> foretelling the calling of the Gentiles, ſpeaketh thus, <hi>The Lord ſhall be known to Egypt, and the Egyptians ſhall know the Lord in that day, and ſhall do ſacrifice and oblation, yea they ſhall vow a vow unto the Lord, and performe it,</hi> Iſa. 19. 21.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Good Covenant-keepers lye very near unto the Lords warme heart, he loves them dearly: <hi>If ye will obey my voice indeed, and keep my Covenant, then ye ſhall be a peculiar treaſure unto me above all people,</hi> Exod. 19. 5. Covenant-keepers are Gods jewels, and all other perſons are accounted as the lumber of the world, in compariſon of them. Men will adventure much to ingratiate them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with great ones; and ſhall not we pay our vows, that we may enjoy the favour, the eſtimation of God, whoſe loving kindnes is better then life?</p>
            <p n="3">3. Hence iſſueth hope to prevaile with the Lord by our pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers: The Pſalmiſt having ſaid, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 65. 1. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto thee O God ſhall the vow be performed;</hi> he adds immediatly, <hi>O thou that heareſt prayers.</hi> And ſo ſoon as this counſell was given, <hi>Pſal</hi> 50. 14. <hi>Pay thy vows unto the moſt High,</hi> in the next verſe, this follows by way of connexion, <hi>And call upon me in the day of trouble, I will deliver thee, and thou ſhalt glorifie me.</hi> As you deſire the audience of your prayers, make you conſcience to pay your vows.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The ſanctification of all our concernments, is a rich privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge appertaining unto honeſt Covenant-keepers: <hi>All the paths of the Lord are mercy and truth, unto them who keep his Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, Pſal.</hi> 25. 10. Gods ſweet mercy, in the performance of his promiſes, runs throug the veins of all his providences for the good of them, who in reference to Covenant, keep touch with him: And who knows fully the worth of this one prerogative; therefore as you deſire a ſhare herein, make conſcience to <hi>pay your vows unto the Lord your God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. What need I deſcend unto any more particulars, ſeeing all the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:113467:10"/> precious promiſes of the Covenant of Goſpel-grace, are aſſured up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, who are faithfull in Covenant with God. The Pſalmiſt having moved this queſtion, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 24. 3. <hi>Who ſhall aſcend into the hill of the Lord, and who ſhall ſtand in his holy place?</hi> part of his anſwer is this; <hi>He that hath not ſworn deceitfully, he ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the bleſſing from the Lord, and righteouſneſſe from the God of his ſalvation:</hi> Therefore be prevailed with through holy ſelfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>love and deſires of bleſſedneſſe, <hi>to pay your vows unto the Lord your God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. And yet once more give me leave to preſſe this argument <hi>ab utili,</hi> upon the hearts of you who are affectionate parents: I know your bowels earn towards your children, and you deſire their good, as your own comfort; now be you well aſſured, that you can take no courſe, which will be more probable to entaile Gods bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing upon your poſterity, then this of conſcientious Covenant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keeping with God. How admirable and deſirable is that promiſe in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103. 17, 18. <hi>The mercy of the Lord is from everlaſting to everlaſting, upon them that fear him, and his righteouſneſſe unto childrens children, to ſuch as keep his covenant?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe benefits of Covenant-keeping I leave in your boſomes, deſiring that through the bleſſing of God, they may do you good.</p>
            <p>I might here mention a further motive, to perſwade the paiment <note place="margin">Motive 4.</note> of vows, from the ſad conſequences of falſeneſſe and unfaithfull<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in this kinde. 1. The Pſalmiſt gives in this as a character of a wicked man, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 55. 20. <hi>He hath broken</hi> (or profaned) <hi>his Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant.</hi> 2. All the ſins of men are greatly aggravated by this circumſtance, that they are not only tranſgreſſions of Gods Law, but violations of their own vows. Thus <hi>Solomon</hi> brands the adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terous woman, <hi>Prov.</hi> 2. 17, <hi>She forgetteth the Covenant of her God.</hi> 3. Breach of Covenant brings Gods burning diſpleaſure up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on people: This thought did awe <hi>Iſrael,</hi> in reference to their raſh League made with the <hi>Gibeonites,</hi> Joſh. 9. 20. <hi>We will let them live, leſt wrath be upon us, becauſe of the oath which we ſware un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. Gods anger in this kinde kindled, may bring a conſumption upon our hopes and comforts. That Item which the <hi>Wiſe man</hi> gives in this caſe ſhould be ſeriouſly minded, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 5. 5, 6. <hi>Better it is that thou ſhouldest not vow, then that thou ſhouldeſt vow and not
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:113467:10"/> pay; wherefore ſhould God be angry at thy voice, and deſtroy the worke of thine hands?</hi> Never were greater works under hand for Church and Common-wealth, in our dayes, or the dayes of our fore-fathers, then are in agitation amongſt us at this day; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let us take heed, leſt our unfaithfullneſſe in our Covenant pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke the Lord to daſh all our endeavours into pieces, with the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appointment of all our golden hopes. Gods curſe is annexed unto his Covenant, to enforce the keeping of it. It is ſaid, <hi>Neh.</hi> 10. 29. <hi>They entered into a curſe, and into an oath to walke in the Law of God.</hi> And the ſword of cruell war is drawn by the hand of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine juſtice, <hi>to avenge the quarrel of the Covenant,</hi> Lev. 26. 25. This ſword of Civil war is eating mans fleſh, and drinking mans blood in this Kingdom at this day; and how can we expect that the Almighty ſhould command it to returne into its ſcabbard, and to be quiet, if we continue careleſſe in keeping Covenant? I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe (beloved) that I have often trembled to thinke upon that diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of Gods ſeverity, in puniſhing <hi>Iſrael with three yeers fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine in Davids time, becauſe Saul had broken the raſh vow,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 2 1.</note> 
               <hi>which the Elders of Iſrael had made long before with the Gibeon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ites.</hi> For thus I reaſon, If the violation of an unadviſed oath with ſubtill ſinfull men, by the poſterity of them who made it, did bring a ſore nationall judgement; what then may we expect from the hand of God, for contradicting both by words and deeds, both by opinions and practices, the ſolemn ſacred League and Covenant which our ſelves have upon deliberation, both made and renewed with man and God? Theſe are weighty conſiderations, and worthy your often and ſerious thoughts, unto which many more might be added; but I forbear the enlarging of this ſubject, becauſe you have ſo fully been acquainted with this matter, by my Reverend bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,<note place="margin">M. <hi>Calamy.</hi>
               </note> who hath largely to ſatisfaction ſet forth the exceeding great danger of truce-breaking, from 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 1. <hi>Covenant-breaking makes the times perillous:</hi> unfaithfullneſſe in Covenant is a Land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtroying, a Kingdom-devouring ſin.</p>
            <p>Now (my beloved) to ſumme up all my arguments: If there be in your hearts, 1. Either reſpect unto the ſacred obligation of a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn vow, 2. Or unto the moſt High poſſeſſour of Heaven and earth. 3. If you either prize the promiſes of his grace, and deſire to be partakers thereof through Chriſt; 4. Or dread the diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veries
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:113467:11"/> of the wrath of the Almighty, and would preſerve your ſelves and your poſterity, your ſelves and the Kingdom from breaking blows of vengeance, <hi>pay your vows unto the Lord your God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe arguments I hope will not be ſleighted by you: God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid, that matters of ſo great, ſo publike concernment, ſhould be diſregarded by them, who profeſſe ſo much zeal and reſpect to God and to his cauſe, unto the proſperity of this famous City, and the wellfare both of Church and Common-wealth, as you <hi>worthy Citizens</hi> have done, and perſevere to do: Therefore I proceed in this ſervice, to ſet down ſome Scripture-rules to guide you in the Faithfull <hi>payment of your vows unto the Lord your God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Pay your good vows <hi>univerſally: Pay thy vows,</hi> ſaith the Pſalm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſt, <note place="margin">Rule 1.</note> 
               <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50. 14. All thy vows, none excepted; whatſoever you have vowed according to his word, you muſt make good according to his command: Thus much is open in the text, <hi>vow and pay unto the Lord your God.</hi> Take good King <hi>Joſiah</hi> for a preſident for your paterne in this particular, of whom it is thus ſaid, upon his covenanting with God, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 34. 33. <hi>And Joſiah took away all the abominations, out of all the countries which pertained to the children of Iſrael, and made all that were preſent in Iſrael to ſwear, even to ſerve the Lord their God.</hi> You ſee that he ſpares nothing, no where within the reach of his authority, which might be diſpleaſing unto his God, or deſtructive to his people. I pray you peruſe the particulars to be oppoſed by vertue of your Covenant, <hi>Popery, Prelacy, Profaneneſſe, Schiſme, Hereſie;</hi> and do not dare to indulge any abomination, which you have vowed to oppoſe: Take heed that no ſinfull biaſſe of near relations, or any ſelf-advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages, take you off from your faithfullneſſe in this kinde. The Holy Ghoſt makes this a character of an heir of Heaven, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 15. 4. <hi>He ſweares and keeps it, though to his own hinderance:</hi> Therefore let not fear of loſing a cuſtomer, a friend, an office, a good bargain, or any other outward advantage, hinder you in keeping your Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant. I will not further enlarge this head, which I leave to your thoughts, but will conclude the rule, with reading the practice of King <hi>Aſa</hi> in the purſuance of his Covenant, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 15. 16. <hi>And alſo concerning Maachah the mother of Aſa the King, he remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved her from being Queen, becauſe ſhe had made an Idol in a grove; And Aſa cut down her Idol, and ſtamped it, and burnt it at the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:113467:11"/> brook Kidron.</hi> There are Idols of mens heads; and of mens hands, there are <hi>Idol-opinions</hi> and <hi>Idol-practices</hi> to be oppoſed by vertue of our Covenant, and you muſt beware leſt through reſpect of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, you prove partiall and unfaithfull.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>When thou ſhalt vow a vow unto the Lord thy God, thou ſhalt not be ſlack to pay it,</hi> Deut. 23. 21. <hi>And, thou ſhalt not defer to</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rule 2.</note> 
               <hi>pay it,</hi> Eccleſ. 5. 4. I might here ſpeak much to perſwade the ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy paiment of our vows; hereby your comfort will be increaſed, and the publike worke of reformation quickned and expedited, your acts will be exemplary and of common influence both thorow the City and the whole Kingdom. How many thouſands enquire, what is done in <hi>London</hi> againſt Popery, Profaneneſſe, Schiſme and Hereſie, in the purſuance of their ſolemn League and Covenant? The ſeaſonableneſſe of an action betters it, doubles it: <hi>Bis dat qui citò dat:</hi> and I may truly ſay in the caſe under hand, <hi>Bis facit qui citò facit:</hi> ply the work of reformation now it is upon the wheels, and you may do much worke in a little time: <hi>principium est di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midium totius;</hi> gain-ſay growing evils, tread upon the Cocka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trice in the ſhell, oppoſe thoſe opinions and practices in the bud, in the birth, which if ſuffered to grow, to live longer, will threaten the peace both of Church and ſtate; by delayes your own guilt will be multiplied and greatened, your hopes of reformation will be enfeebled, and the whole Kingdom endangered: Buſineſſes of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity call for quick diſpatch? and is there any worke of greater concernment, then the worke of your God, in endeavouring your own reformation, and the reformation of his Church according to his word, which is the matter of your Covenant? I remember the words of <hi>Moſes</hi> to <hi>Aaron, Go quickly to the Congregation, for there is wrath gone out from the Lord, the plague is begun, Num.</hi> 16. 46. And it is ſaid that <hi>Aaron did run.</hi> Blame me not, but bear with me, I beſeech you, if I appear warme, in perſwading your ſpeed in acting according to your Covenant, for I ſpeak for the ſafety of a ſinking Kingdom. Are we not all on a flame? which way can you caſt your eyes, but you ſhall ſee the ſparkes of unbro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly contentions, riſing as out of a furnace? Alas, alas, we ſhall burne into aſhes, and from confuſions fall into a ruinous heape, if through Gods bleſſing upon Covenant-keeping-endeavours, our miſery be not prevented.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:113467:12"/>
            <p>Pay your vows <hi>boldly,</hi> with ſo much openneſſe, that the wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of your bonds may be witneſſes likewiſe of your faithfull<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe <note place="margin">Rule 3.</note> in diſcharging them: The reſolution of <hi>David</hi> is herein imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, which he expreſſeth once and again in the ſame Pſalme, <hi>I will pay my vows unto the Lord in the preſence of all his people, in the preſence of all his people, yea in the midst of thee, O Jeruſalem, Pſal.</hi> 116. 14, 18, 19. Is it any ſhame for a man to be honeſt, and to pay his debts? Wherefore then ſhould men be loth to appear in the purſuance of their Covenants? Act ſo publikely, ſo couragiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for a full reformation according to the word of God, and againſt Malignancy, Sedition, Hereſie, together with all other things de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive to the welfare of the three Kingdoms, that both City and Countrey may underſtand your undaunted reſolutions to keep Covenant with your God: And if in this way of zeal and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullneſſe, you ſhould meet with checks and affronts, make ye that anſwer unto your oppoſers, which brave-ſpirited <hi>David</hi> made unto mocking <hi>Michal, If this be to be vile, I will yet be more vile,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 6.</p>
            <p>Keep Covenant with the Lord <hi>conſcientiouſly:</hi> Have reſpect unto God in paying as in making vows: My text holds forth this <note place="margin">Rule 4.</note> openly, as many other parallel Scriptures, which I have formerly made uſe of. Whatſoever we do, which is materially comprehend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in our Covenant, we ſhould do it, <hi>becauſe of the oath of God, Eccleſ.</hi> 8. 2. Do not only intend man-pleaſing, or ſelfe-ſeeking in the purſuance of your Covenant; be not popular and vain-glorious, but ſincere and ſingle-hearted in this ſervice. As in other acts of obedience, ſo in this of Covenant-keeping, have an eye unto your heavenly father <hi>who ſees in ſecreet, and he will reward you openly.</hi> God forbid, God forbid that any one of you ſhould act againſt your brethren with an envious or malicious ſpirit, under pretence of making good your Covenant. O take heed unto your ſelves, that you diſgrace not this holy ordinance, nor open the mouths of them, who maligne our Covenant, and would upon ſuch like obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, reproachfully aſperſe both you and it. I will conclude this rule, with the caution given by worthy <hi>Nehemiah: Ought ye not to walke in the fear of our God, becauſe of the reproach of our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies?</hi> Neh. 5. 9.</p>
            <p>Be vigorous in the payment of your vows: The command of <note place="margin">Rule 5.</note>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:113467:12"/> God given unto <hi>Moſes</hi> for the guiding of this buſineſſe, is here very conſiderable, <hi>Le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 22. 21. <hi>Whoſoever offereth a ſacrifice to accompliſh his vow, it ſhall be perfect to be accepted, there ſhall be no blemiſh in it.</hi> When you pay your debts to God, bring your beſt coyn; put not off your light gold to God; imploy and improve your very beſt for your God; give him the flower of your wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, ſtrength, authority and intereſts; ſit down and conſider where your chiefeſt ability lyes, and reſolve with that to pay your vows. Say thus unto your own ſouls ſeriouſly in ſecret; I will beat mine own brains by ſtudy, I will ſtir up my beſt friends by importunity, and I will induſtriouſly take all courſes within the compaſſe of my generall and particular calling, that my ſelfe and my family, that this Church and Common-wealth may be reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and that unity betwixt <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> may be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved according to <hi>the ſolemne League and Covenant:</hi> to quicken your care in this kinde, remember thoſe ſmart words, <hi>Mal.</hi> 1. 14. <hi>Curſed be the deceiver, who hath a male in his flock, and voweth and ſacrificeth unto the Lord a corrupt thing: for I am a great King, ſaith the Lord of hoſts, and my Name is dreadfull among the heathen.</hi> Look to it therefore, I beſeech you, thinke not to put God off, with ſupine, ſuperficiall ſleightneſſe in Covenant-keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: If you have male-conſolations, male-affections, male-en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours, male-adventures for other things, God will not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept your female, your cold, faint, feeble actings for him, in the payment of your vows: Therefore if you have any talent bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then ordinary, trade that for your God, in the purſuance of your Covenant.</p>
            <p>Keep Covenant with the Lord <hi>conſtantly: I will ſing praiſes</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rule 6.</note> 
               <hi>to thy Name for ever</hi> (ſaith <hi>David,) that I may daily performe my vows,</hi> Pſal 61. 8. you muſt not be like thoſe Tenants, who bring in their rents readily, and miſſe not a day for the firſt year, but grow careleſſe afterward, in making paiment according to their compacts and agreements. The ſame heat which is in your hearts to day (<hi>this day of your Covenant-renewing,</hi>) for reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation according to Gods word, and againſt the hindrances and hinderers thereof, muſt be kept burning in your boſomes ſo long as you ſhall live. It is to be bewailed with tears of blood, that the tract of time takes off the fervency of mens ſpirits for God
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:113467:13"/> in the worke of vowed-reformation. How have we loſt our firſt love? How is our zeal for good, and againſt evil of late abated? The time was, when our Covenant was much in our thoughts, much in our mouthes, when we moved others, and provoked our ſelves to make conſcience to keep it: but now (<hi>I am aſhamed to speake it,</hi>) our Covenant is forgotten, our Covenant is laid aſide; yea (O that I had not occaſion to add) many repent their taking of the Covenant, and ſome are not afraid to plead againſt it: I heartily wiſh, that the true cauſes of this great change were well enquired after. My beloved, Is Church-reformation ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Scripture grown leſſe deſireable? Are pure ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces leſſe lovely in our eyes? Is there now leſſe danger of our un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doing by <hi>malignancy, popery, diviſions and hereſie,</hi> then hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore? <hi>Remember, I pray you, from whence you are fallen, and do your first works,</hi> in reference to your Covenant, the obligation whereof continues upon your conſciences. Our God <hi>keeps Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant to a thouſand generations,</hi> Deut. 7. 9. Let his example in this particular perſwade your conſtancy. <hi>Be not weary of well doing;</hi> be not diſcouraged by diſappointments<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> be not beaten off by difficulties, delayes, oppoſitions; but proceed according to your callings and conditions, to promote that bleſſed reformation which is under hand: <hi>In due time you ſhall reap, if you faint not; Finis coronat opus;</hi> Be you faithfull in your Covenant unto death, and you ſhall receive the crown of life.</p>
            <p>I have done with my Rules; now give me leave to give in ſome few helps that you may act accordingly, and I will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude all.</p>
            <p>That you may be able to keep touch with God in point of Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, take theſe very ſhort directions.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Worke well into your hearts the knowledge of all the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned <note place="margin">Directions.</note> particulars produced to perſwade Covenant-keeping: <hi>A wiſe man</hi> (ſaith <hi>Solomon) is ſtrong, yea, a man of knowledge increaſeth strength</hi> (or ſtrengtheneth might,) <hi>Prov.</hi> 24. 5. Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture-truths clearly underſtood, convey according to Gods Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, ſpirituall abilities into the ſouls of men to act accordingly; As the warme beams of the ſummer ſun adminiſter vivacity to the creatures, both vegetative and ſenſitive: Therefore I humbly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe you, to put your ſelves often under the power of thoſe truths,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:113467:13"/> which may convince you of the neceſſity and equity of paying your vows unto the Lord your God; and I doubt not, but by means of ſerious meditation, you ſhall finde more activity herein to do your duty: <hi>While I was muſing</hi> (ſaith <hi>David) the fire burned, Pſal.</hi> 39. 3. The bellows of meditation will produce the flame of zeal, out of the ſmall heat of holy deſires to keep Covenant with God.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Act conſcientiouſly, according to that meaſure of ſtrength which you have received. We all know by experience, that exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe increaſeth bodily ſtrength, and queſtionleſſe Chriſtians finde the truth hereof in their ſouls. <hi>Solomon</hi> aſſures us, <hi>Prov.</hi> 10. 29. <hi>The way of the Lord is ſtrength to the upright:</hi> The further we walke on in the wayes of faithfullneſſe with God, and for God, the more able we ſhall be to make good our foederall engagements un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his Majeſty. Do you not all remember that famous ſtory of the well-minded widow, lamenting her inability to pay her debts, whoſe little ſtock of oyl was multiplied by pouring forth, 2 <hi>King.</hi> 4. I beſeech you make a ſpirituall improvement of this experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; give out thoſe gifts, graces, which you have received in the paiment of your vows, and be you confident of increaſe: In this ſenſe <hi>habenti dabitur;</hi> trade your two talents, or your five for your Maſters uſe, and they ſhall be doubled, <hi>ariſe and be doing, and the Lord will be with you.</hi> Many of you know to your comfort, that a ſmall ſtock traded, is grown up to a great eſtate; I pray you make practicall application.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Minde your ſelves, and minde one another often of your ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne Covenant: This was Gods own direction in this caſe, 2 <hi>King.</hi> 17. 39, <hi>The Covenant which I have made with you, ye ſhall not forget.</hi> Among men, many promiſes are not performed, becauſe they are not remembred: And ſo it is likewiſe in many of our obligations unto God, forgetfullneſſe is ſometimes one cauſe of ſome unfaithfullneſſe. The Pſalmiſts connexion, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103. 18. is conſiderable; <hi>Thoſe that keep his Covenant, and thoſe who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member his Commandements to do them.</hi> There is an Order of Parliament, requiring Miniſters to reade the ſolemne League and Covenant in the Congregation, upon our Monethly Faſt dayes; And I humbly move, that there may be an Order of the Common-Councel of this famous City, that the Covenant which you this
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:113467:14"/> day renew, may once at leaſt in every quarter of the year be read amongſt you; by means hereof, you would be quickned to appear both jointly and ſeverally, in courſes to promote both private and publike reformation according to your Covenant.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Seek ſtrength from Heaven, by faith and prayer: The holy Apoſtle, holding up to Jeſus Chriſt by humble confidence, could ſay, <hi>I can do all through Christ strengthening me,</hi> Phil. 4. 13. And the Pſalmiſt makes this report of the ſucceſſe of his prayer; <hi>In the day when I cried, thou anſweredſt me, and strengthenedst me with ſtrength in my ſoul,</hi> Pſal. 138. 3. Your ſelves beſt know, wherein Covenant-keeping ſticks moſt with your ſelves, you are acquainted with your own <hi>remoraes,</hi> your own difficulties in this ſervice. Conſider that your helpe lies in the Lord your God, therefore fetch it thence by fervent believing prayers; plead the promiſes of Gods Covenant with you through Chriſt, that you through him may be able to deal faithfully, to do wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily; and be you confident that the Lord will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be wanting unto the ſoul which ſeeks him in truth, <hi>He hath not ſaid to the houſe of Jacob, Seek ye me in vain.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:113467:14"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
